Vanessa A. Marshall Papers VHP2006/11
CCSU Veterans History Project
Vanessa A. Marshall Papers
Bulk, 1964-1978
1964 - 1986, 2006
VHP2006/11
CCSU Veterans History Project
23.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of Venessa A. Marshall as a military nurse during Vietnam War period. The collection contains video of an oral history interview, personal papers such as diploma and certificate, and photographs.
Marshall, Vanessa A., (Vanessa Ann), 1935 -
Biographical/Historical note
Vanessa A. Marshall enlisted in the United States Army in 1964. She entered the army as an officer, because she had already obtained a Bachelors degree in nursing and had five years of experience. She went to basic training in Ft. Sam Houston, TX, where she was a platoon leader, and learned field techniques for dressing wounds in combat situations. After basic training she was stationed at a large military hospital in San Francisco where she worked in a surgical ward for just under a year. She was then transferred to Japan, just as the war in Vietnam was escalating. She stayed at the hospital in Japan for three years, where they treated wounded soldiers from Vietnam, in what was supposed to be a 100 bed hospital, but ended up accommodating far more wounded men. When she was sent back to the U.S. in 1967 she was able to enlist as regular army, and obtained a master's degree in midwifery from Yale University as a result. She was the first military nurse in Yale's nursing school. She moved around the country, practicing midwifery at many military hospitals, and delivered over 200 babies in about two years. She also spent 18 months on a military base in Germany, before she was discharged in 1978. She then joined the reserves, and obtained a doctorate in Public Health from Harvard, before retiring from the military in 1986. Since her discharge she has taught at Yale, and set up a midwifery masters program at University of Rhode Island among other accomplishments.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Letterman General Hospital (San Francisco, Calif.).; United States. Army Nurse Corps.; United States. Army.; Fort Sam Houston (Tex.); Germany; Japan; Midwifery; Military nursing -- United States -- History; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Personal narrative, American; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Women; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Medical care.; Zama-shi (Japan)
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/11.I
  - Appointment of Vanessa Marshall as a Reserve Commissioned Officer, Feb. 3, 1964; VHP2006/11.I.1
  - Diploma for completion of the Army Nurse Corps Officer Basic Course, May 8, 1964; VHP2006/11.I.2
  - Certificate of Shipboard Instructor Training, Dec. 10, 1965; VHP2006/11.I.3
  - Diploma for Army Medical Service Officer Advanced Course, Jun. 28, 1968; VHP2006/11.I.4
  - Certificate for Directors of Clinical Nursing Specialty Course, Mar. 16, 1973; VHP2006/11.I.5
  - Diploma for Health Care Assessment course, Jun. 25, 1976; VHP2006/11.I.6
  - Honorable Discharge from the United States Army, Mar. 1, 1978; VHP2006/11.I.7
  - Appointment of Major, Reserve, Mar. 2, 1978; VHP2006/11.I.8
  - Diploma for Command and General Staff Officer Course, Mar. 9, 1981; VHP2006/11.I.9
  - Diploma for Health Care Administration Course, May 6, 1985; VHP2006/11.I.10
  - Certificate of appreciation from chief Army Reserve, Jan 21, 1986; VHP2006/11.I.11
  - Retried reserve certificate, Jan 21, 1986; VHP2006/11.I.12
  - Retried reserve certificate, Jan 21, 1986; VHP2006/11.I.13
  - Certificate of retirement from the US Army, Dec. 16, 1995; VHP2006/11.I.14
  - Interview synopsis, Sep. 13, 2006; VHP2006/11.I.15
- Series II: Multi-Media, VHP2006/11.II
  - Suberies A: Still Images, VHP2006/11.II
    - Vanessa Marshall at Letterman General Hospital, Presidio, San Francisco, CA, 1964; VHP2006/11.II.1
    - Vanessa Marshall with her first car. San Francisco, CA, 1964; VHP2006/11.II.2
    - Vanessa Marshall, Platoon Leader (front and center) Platoon leader. Fort Sam Houston, San Antonio, TX, April 1964; VHP2006/11.II.3
    - Vanessa Marshall running the orthopedic ward. U.S. Army Hospital, Camp Zama, Japan, 1967; VHP2006/11.II.4
    - Vanessa Marshall in Germany with her two dogs while working at Bad Cannstatt 5th General Hospital. Gerlingen, Germany, 1973; VHP2006/11.II.5
    - ANC Officer Basic Class 4 Medical Field Service School Brooke Army Medical Center Fort Sam Houston, TX, March 1964; VHP2006/11.II.6
    - AMEDS Officer Advanced Class #3 Section II Brooke Army Medical Center Fort Sam Houston, Texas, June 1968; VHP2006/11.II.7
    - Vanessa Marshall at her home in Trumbull, CT, 2006; VHP2006/11.II.8
  - Suberies B: Moving Images, VHP2006/11.IIb
    - Oral history interview with Vanessna A. Marshall, Sep. 13, 2006; VHP2006/11.IIb.1; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2006/11, Box VHP Interview 2006)